We have gathered here on the occassion of Ram Navami
我们在罗摩 Navamai 的日子 聚集在这里
everybody has said
每个人都说
Mother please tell us about Shri Ram
母亲 请告诉我们有关罗摩的事情
As you know that Shri Rama has taken a very important place in our chakras
你也知道 罗摩在我们的轮穴 占很重要的位置
He is sitting on our right heart
祂坐在我们的右心轮
Shri Rama has taken a place of a father
罗摩代表父亲的位置
so lack of father's duty and love can cause a catch of this chakra
因此 缺乏父亲的责任和爱能令 这个轮穴阻塞
In Sahaja Yoga we can understand that Rama and all other gods
在霎哈嘉瑜伽 我们能明白罗摩和其他神祇
came on earth with different power (shakti),
以各种力量降临地球
they came to do their jobs
祂们肩负任务而来
In the sense Shri Rama has a special job
为此 罗摩有一份特别的任务
Socrates has said benevolent king has to come
就如稣格拉底所说 仁爱厚道的国王要来
For that Shri Rama came
罗摩就是 代表这位仁爱厚道的国王
Shri Rama came in complete human form
祂以人类的形相来
He even forgot that
祂甚至忘记
he is a incarnation of Shri Vishnu He was made to be forgotten
自己是毗湿奴的降世 就是要使祂忘记
But he was Purushottam on earth (perfect human being)
祂是地球上的Purushottam (理想的人类)
you all must have heard of his qualities and his childhood
你们必定听过祂的品格 和祂童年的事迹
In Sahaja yoga when we worship any god
在霎哈嘉瑜伽 当我们敬拜任何神祇
what quality we gain from them
我们能从祂们身上取得什么品质
which qualities we will receive?
我们会吸收到祂们的那种品质
Shri Rama has many
罗摩有很多特质
One that he was ideal another that he is a king
其一祂是榜样典范 其二祂是国王
he kept his people higher than himself
祂视祂的子民比自己更高
than his wife and children
也比祂的妻儿高
If politicians today
若今天的政客
understand this point
能明白这一点
they wouldn't be called selfish
他们就不会被称呼为自私
they wouldn't be selfish
他们就不会自私
would be follower of Dharma.
亦会是正法的追随者
Nobody has followed
直至今天
Shri Rama as a role model till today
没有人追随或视罗摩为典范榜样
By singing his bhajans
透过唱祂的拜赞歌
or building an institutions and temples in his name
以祂之名建立机构和建造庙宇
Shri Rama come to you?
罗摩能否来到你身上
Do you get his light in your life?
你有否在你的生命里 取得祂的光
Only sahaj yogi can bring the light of Shri Rama into the attention
只有霎哈嘉瑜伽士能把罗摩的光 带进我们的注意力里
He is totally beyond
祂完全超越
Basically all the deities are free from papas and punyas
基本上 所有神祇都免于 papas(罪孽)和punyas(功德)
so called sins they never sin
所谓的罪孽 祂们从来都没有罪
Shri Krishna killed many people
就如克里希纳杀死很多人
Shri Rama killed Ravana
罗摩则杀死拉伐那
It can be a sin in worldly sense
这些事情以俗世来看是罪孽
but not in the eyes of god
但神不是这样看
As they destroy and remove evils they have rights to do anything
因为祂们毁灭邪恶 把坏事物移除 祂们有权做任何事
When Devi slayed Rakshas she has committed a sin?
就如女神杀掉很多恶魔 祂是否犯了罪
Their work is to destroy the rakshas and protect the saints
祂们的工作 就是毁灭恶魔和保护圣人
In Shri Rama's life Ahilya's saving is the most important
在罗摩的一生 作为 Ahilya的拯救者是最重要的
she was cursed by her husband
她被她的丈夫咀咒
In those times if any women goes out of dharma
那时候 若任何女士偏离正法
and if her husband is high saint he could curse
而她的丈夫又是 位处高位的圣人 他就能咀咒人
But Ahillya was blamed falsely
但他却错误地责怪她
And she was made into stone falsely
把她变成石头
So shri Rama saved Ahilya
罗摩因此拯救Ahilya
Especially his quality to have only one wife
特别的是祂只有一个妻子
his love to one wife must be understood
我们要明白祂只爱一个妻子
Even though he knew Sitaji is Mahalaxmi she herself is a Goddess
即使祂知道悉旦是摩诃拉希什米 的其中一个形相 她是女神
But as a Human he never looked at any other women but his wife
罗摩在人的形相时 除祂的妻子外 祂从不看其他女人
When we talk about Rama we should have the husband pure
当我们谈罗摩时 我们就要有这份丈夫的洁净
To worships shri Rama
要敬拜罗摩
Women should have the same faith in husbands as Sitaji used to
女人要对她的丈夫如悉旦对她的 丈夫那样 有同样的信任
Husbands also need the quality of Shri Ram who believed one wife
同样 丈夫也要像罗摩 只能有一个妻子
Not difficult for sahaja yogis
对霎哈嘉瑜伽士来说 不难做到
Women should be respected Have respect for wifes
女人要受到尊重 对妻子要尊重
When Ravana kidnapped Sitaji
当拉伐那绑架悉旦
Shri Rama felt his duty to rescue her
罗摩感到有责任拯救她
But in his kingdom he was so just that
但对祂的子民来说
For people he left her after spending so many years to rescue
祂要离开多年来拯救她
As Sitaji herself a Devi so there's no effect
悉旦也是女神 离开她 不会有任何严重的后果
So Shri Rama did it
罗摩因此离开她
to keep the benevolence of public opinion
为了大众的福祉
that society wouln't accpect the women
不然社会不会接受
who are questioned.
受质疑的女人
Although she is a Devi Pure and Nirmala
虽然她是女神 纯洁和 Nirmala
Later that Sita also left him somehow
之后 不知何故 悉旦也离开祂
She left him as a woman and Shri Rama as a man
她就如女人般离开祂 罗摩亦如男人般离开她
Sitaji disappeared into the mother earth and Shri Rama went into River Sarayu
悉旦消失在大地之母里 而罗摩则跳进 Sarayu河
Their life is very eventful and full of Miracles
祂们的一生多姿多彩 充满奇迹
You see how shri Sita and Rama have good attitude and are faithful each other
你看到祂们对待对方的态度 互相忠诚
Even if she was left Sita thought it her duty
即使她离开 悉旦认为这是她的责任
She never complained or talked ill of him
她从不投诉罗摩 或说祂坏话
And effortlessly she has raised her children
她毫不费力的从容地 养育她的孩子
Shri Rama's children are called Luv and Kush
罗摩的孩子名为Luv 和Kush
They came as devotees and we can see them as disciples
他们以虔敬者来到这个世界 我们能视他们为门徒
They represents Shisya (disciples)
他们代表 Shisya (门徒)和门徒的力量
the power of Shisya so we can be disciple of someone
因此我们能成为某人的门徒
As disciples they learned archery when they were small
作为门徒 他们在很年幼时已经学习射箭
And learned Ramayana and got proficiency in the music
学习罗摩衍那 对音乐很熟练
Showing the disciples must surrender completely to the Guru
这显示门徒必须完全顺服委身于 他们的导师
We also have a disciples in us
我们内在亦有门徒
They were  completely surrendered to the Mother who is Shakti
他们完全顺服于母亲 她是力量
Even they were about to fight against Shri Rama
他们还准备就诸 为母亲与罗摩一起战斗
they kept Mother highest in the world
他们视母亲为全世界最伟大的
The mother cared them and made them completely dharmic
母亲养育他们 照顾他们 令他们坚守正法
It was her first duty
这是她首要的责任
Not like today wives just cry "my husband left me"
不像今天的妻子 只会日夜都在哭我的丈夫离开我
But with husband they fight always and if he leaves they will cry
但当丈夫回来 她们就会与他 时刻争吵 一旦他离开 她们就哭
He has left no problem I have children, I will care for them
若他离开 没问题 我有孩子 我要照顾他们
they will get all they need
孩子会得到他们一切所需
Sitaj's life was special with bravery and strength
悉旦的人生很特别 充满勇气和毅力
Every woman must have it
每个女人都要有 这份勇气和毅力
Even if you are separated with your husband or far away
即使你与丈夫分开 或他远离你
there shouldn't be any loss or shortage for children
这应不会有任何损失 对孩子亦没有任何缺失
Because her duty is the most important thing
因为她对孩子的责任 是最重要的
We shouldn't give up most important thing
我们不应放弃最重要的事情
In sahaja yoga all women should get this power
在霎哈嘉瑜伽 所有女人都要取得这力量
Shri Rama's life was very pure and Nirmal
罗摩的人生是很纯洁和 Nirmal
he gave up everything for his wife
祂为妻子放弃一切
His wife had gone, he had to live alone and he had to leave her
祂的妻子走了 祂要独自生活 祂必须离开她
He gave up all the comforts of the life
祂放弃生活上的一切舒适
You know he used to sleep on grass, on floor and walked barefeet
你也知道 祂常常睡在草地上 睡在地上 赤脚行走
and wear clothes like saints
也常常穿得像圣人
All these are not stories it's a fact
所有这些都不是故事 是事实
In India many people used to have high standard life
在印度 很多人过着很高标准的生活
and they have never thought about small and low level things
他们从未想过微小低层次的事物
But all these ideals of our country have beccome fake
但我们国家 这些典范 却已经变得虚假
By singing bhajans to Ram we think we are done
透过向罗摩唱拜赞歌 我们以为自己已经做到
we have got a kind of hypocracy
这是一种伪善
In countries without these ideals
没有这些典范的国家
people try to become the ideals correcting themselves
人们尝试想成为典范 他们改正自己
If you have the ideal in front of us
若你们有典范榜样在前
you don't  become Shri Rama or Krishna
我们不能成为罗摩或克里希纳
or you have anything to do with them
或与祂们有任何关系
We feel like that
我们有这种感受
But if we have Shri Rama inside his light can be in our attention
若我们内在有罗摩 祂的光可以在我们注意力里
Let's understand
让我们理解
the circumstances when Shri Rama came on earth
罗摩在什么情况下 降临这个地球
Sahaja Yogi must understand
霎哈嘉瑜伽士必须明白
If we get Shri Rama's state All our political problems will go
若我们能取得罗摩的状态 我们所有的政治问题都会消失
when we decide to become like shri Rama
当我们决定变得像罗摩
Then everyone becomes good
那么每个人都变成好人
firstly dharma, success and education then the ideals
他们先得到正法 取得成功 受到教育 成为典范
for that he made his life very idealistic
为此 祂令自己的人生很理想
When someone tells you something but he doesn't do it himself
当某人对你说了一些 他们也做不到的事情
Then how can you trust him and get his quality
你会否相信他并以他为榜样
There are many people who say we believe in this and that
很多人说 我相信这样 相信那样
But they are opposite
他们却有相反的言行
Followers of Ram seems to be the biggest fraud politician and they have many wives, impossible
罗摩的追随者看来是 最大的骗子政客 他们有很多妻子 没可能是这样的
What is the duty of Sahaja Yogis' life?
因此 什么是霎哈嘉瑜伽士的责任
we have to bring the light of god in our attention
我们要把神的光 带进我们的注意力
We must see and behave as Shri Rama
我们必须以罗摩的角度看事物 言行举止亦要像祂
What would Shri Rama or Sita do in this situation
若这种事情发生 罗摩和悉旦会怎样做
What would Sita ji say?
悉旦会说什么
How would Sita behave? She is also Gruhlaxmi
她会有怎样的言行 她也是古哈拉希什米
As you know Sitaji took many births
你也知道 悉旦多次降世
Gruhlaxmi was in the form of Fatima-bi
这些古哈拉希什米的降世中 有法蒂玛的形相
She was humbly in the house but all dharma was done by her power
她谦卑的在家里 但所有正法的 工作都是以她的力量来做的
Not necessary for her to go out and give big lectures
她不需要外出 作重大的演说
You can do that work at home with children relatives and friends
你能在家里 与孩子 亲人和朋友做这工作
you can spread sahaja Yoga at the house
你可以在家里传扬霎哈嘉瑜伽
After getting all of it you can go out to society
在拥有力量之后 你可以进入社区
But ladies have to have purity like Sitaji first
但首先 女士要有悉旦的纯洁
First thing of the purity is motherhood and love
纯真首先是母性和爱
When she was in exile never complained that my husband doesn't earn
当她与丈夫被流放到森林里 她从不投诉 我的丈夫没有赚钱
He doesn't do this he doesn't buy this and that
他没有这样做 他没有买这东西 那东西
If he is in jungle so I am What he will eat I wil
若他留在森林 我也要留在森林 他吃什么 我也吃什么
I don't eat before him I serve him first
我不会在他面前吃 我会伺候他先吃
and  brother in law then I will eat
也会伺候我丈夫的兄弟 之后我才吃
Nowadays women think there is much pressure of the work But it is not
现在女人以为这种工作 给她们压力 但不是这样
A woman is like earth element she can absorb
女人就像土元素 她能吸收
So many are given by the earth
大地给予我们的一切
In the same way women are like the earth
同样 女人亦要像大地
We have got so many powers that we can take everything inside
我们拥有很多力量 我们内在能包容一切
and shower the rain of love God has given us the power
亦能洒下爱之雨 神赐予我们力量
For example this fan is moving Which one is greater, the power or fan?
例如 风扇在移动 电力还是风扇比较了不起
If you think fan is greater as  it's moving Then it's wrong
若你认为因为风扇在动 所以它更了不起 你错了
Women are ocean of shakti
女人是力量的海洋
With that support Men does their work
得到她的支持 男人才能做好他的工作
They are potential and kinetic Women are potential and men are kinetic
有种说法是潜在和动力 潜在的是女人 男人则是动力
But if you start running like them
若你开始像他们那样跑
It's not good No need for women
就不大好 女人没必要这样
Each one is unique but equally important But women can be good for both
男女各有独特之处 亦同样重要 女人两者都能做好
When the time comes women can be more productive
当时候到了 女人可以更有生产力
In Maharashtra there was a 17-year-old widow named Tarabai
在马哈拉施特拉邦 有个名为Tarabai的十七岁寡妇
She was the daughter-in-law of Shivaji
她是悉旦(Shivaji)的媳妇
Only she could defeat Aurangzeb
只有她打败过Aurangzeb
Her grave was built
她的坟墓建在Aurangabaad
You must understand women can keep all her power within her to become ferocious
你必须明白 女人把所有力量保存在内 她就变得勇猛
But  if she waste her powers in fighting, arguing, complaining or in frivolous things
但若她把她的力量浪费在 争斗上 争辩上 投诉上 或细微琐碎的事情上
then her power would be gone
那么她的力量就会消失
Women are so powerful that she can work more than men if she want
女人是那么有力量 若她想 她能比男人做得更多
But first of all she must respect her powers
但首先 她要尊重自己的力量
by scattering and wasting she becomes powerless
若她分散和浪费自己的力量 她真的变得毫无力量
this kind of woman is not good
这种女人不好
Women's job is very important and full of dignity
女人的工作是很重要的 充满尊贵
Women should be very modest and very wise
女人要很温和 很有智慧
Let Men use bad words but women cannot
让男人说坏话吧 女人不能说
Men can argue and would fight let them do but not Women
男人会争辩 亦会打架 让他们这样吧 但女人不能
Their job is to make peace, protection and helping people
她们的工作是制造和平 保护人 帮助人
She is like shield not like sword and sword cannot be shield
她像盾牌 不是像剑 剑不能是盾牌
Shield is greater than sword as shield can bear the sword
盾牌比剑更了不起 因为盾牌能抵抗剑的攻击
Sword can be broken but not shield
剑会折断但盾牌不会
So her most important power is humility
所以她最重要的力量是谦卑
With humility comes all the powers
透过谦卑 所有力量都会来
It's not difficult for sahaj yogis not at all
对霎哈嘉瑜伽士这不困难 完全不困难
I see many sahaja yoginis chat a lot
我看到很多女霎哈嘉瑜伽士 闲聊太多
anywhere they will chat with men
在任何地方 她们都能与男人闲聊
"Mother help me" "what happened"
母亲 请帮我  什么事
"The lady talks a lot please help me"
这个女人说话大多 请帮我
"I am tired of her"
我对她很厌倦
There isn't much to talk with men What's the need?
没有太多事情可以和男人谈 有什么需要说些无聊话
Among women also
即使女人之间亦不用说太多话
In sahaja yoga men study more
在霎哈嘉瑜伽 男人更要学习
About Sahaja Yoga and the chakras
什么是霎哈嘉瑜伽什么是轮穴
Which chakra is driving people and is catching?
什么轮穴在驱动人 什么轮穴有阻塞
Man knows all women would be left behind
男人懂所有知识 女人便会落后
Women must learn
女人也要学习这些知识
For men Shri Rama is our ideal
就男人而言 罗摩是我们的典范
In this sense Muslims are amazing
就此穆斯林真的令人很惊讶
I don't want to say bad things
我不想说坏话
Say if you go to Riyad no  Muslim will see you
例如 若你到 Ryaad 没一个穆斯林会看你
they will respect women If women are crossing the street
他们非常尊重妇女 若有女人要过马路
they will stop the car respecting women
他们会把车子停下来 那里尊重妇女
But here it's opposite I don't know why
我不知道为何这里的人对妇女 有相反的态度
we see women with some intention
我们看女人是有企图的
Seeing every woman they will break the neck
即使他们的颈子折断 也会不停的看
It's a big sin to see every woman
这样看女人是很大的罪孽
In sahaja yoga it's prohibited completely
在霎哈嘉瑜伽是禁止这样做 完全禁止这样做
Firstly you will spoil your eyes and Sahaja Yoga
首先 这样做你会破坏 你的眼睛和霎哈嘉瑜伽
Otherwise you may become blind
不然 或许你们会盲眼
Sometimes I see people have wandering eyes
有时 我看到人们有摇摆不定的眼神
While talking eyes are wandering women too
在说话时 眼神摇摆不定 女人也一样
The biggest loss is your attention
最大的损失是你的注意力
Your attention goes here and there
你的注意力四处放
then what's the use of self-realization
那么 有自觉又有何用
Without concentration Chitta can't be active
若你的注意力不集中 就不能起作用
Concentration must be obtained
注意力必须集中
In the west the disease is more common among men
在西方 这种疾病在男人间很普遍
Western yogis are not alike They know it's bad
西方的霎哈嘉瑜伽士并不相似 他们知道这是很坏的
They asked me the solution
他们问我有什么解决办法
Look at only ground and up to 3 feets you don't have to see above
你们只要看着地面 直到三尺 不看三尺以上
Look at the ground Yogis are walking looking at the ground abroad
看着地面 瑜伽士走路时看着地面
You see all good things, flowers and children Nothing to see above
就能看到好东西 看到花朵 孩子上面没什么好看
So, that's how you should control your chitta
你就是这样控制你的注意力
Shri Rama didn't need it If you have a respect to shri Rama
罗摩不需要这样 若你尊重罗摩
You must control your chitta like him
就必须像祂那样控制你的注意力
Tell your wife you respect her as shakti But she has to deserve it
告诉你的妻子 你尊重她作为力量 但她要值得受尊重
"Yatr naryan pujante tatr ramante devata"
Yatr naryan pujante tatr ramante devata
"Where women are respected resides god" But they have to be respectable
即哪里的妇女受到尊重 哪里就有神 但她们要值得受尊重
Please sit down
请坐下
Don't move during Puja
崇拜时不要四处走
If the woman is worshipable "Pujyante" means "worshipable"
若女人值得受敬拜 "Pujyante" 意思是值得受敬拜
Who like to worship a bad woman cruel Rakshasi?
谁会喜欢敬拜坏女人 残忍的恶魔
Those who are worshpable should be worshipped There resides gods
我们要敬拜值得受敬拜的人 那里有神在
Firstly they are mothers of children
首先 她们是孩子的母亲
If husband scolds wife in front of children
若丈夫在孩子面前讽刺他的妻子
then children will never respect mother
孩子就不会尊重他们的母亲
It's prime minister and deputy minister
这是总理或副总理
Women shouldn't insult her husband too
女人也不应侮辱她的丈夫
Power goes to children from father
力量是父亲给孩子的
Without this basic understanding they fight to take control
没有这基本的理解 他们会因为想掌管事而打架
If woman knows handling of man there won't be any fights
若女人知道怎样应对男人 就不会有任何争吵
Handling men is very easy as they are just like children
应付男人很容易 因为男人就像孩子
they are innocent like children
他们纯真如孩子
By talking nonsense you can't handle them
向他们说些荒唐的说话 你不能应付他们
You must forgive them as children
你要像原谅孩子般原谅他们
If they fight outside they get troubled
若他们在外面与别人争吵 他们会有麻烦
They can get angry only to wife
他们只能生妻子气
Getting angry at home is OK
在家里生气还可以
Until you get this feeling, you cannot have mutual understanding, love and joy
除非你有这种感觉 不然你们是不能互相了解体谅 相亲相爱和有喜乐
Men also should care for wife's needs
男人亦要关心妻子的需要
if wife is wrong, husband has duty to say no "It's wrong, I won't do this"
若妻子错了 丈夫有责任说不 这是错的 我不会这样做
But no need to fight on small things It doesn't look good as sahaja yogis
没必要为一些琐事争吵 这样对霎哈嘉瑜伽士来说不大好看
I am surprised that Sahaja couples fight each other
我很惊讶 霎哈嘉瑜伽的夫妇争吵
They come to complain about each other
他们投诉对方
How come sahaja couple cannot be together peacefully while I'm talking about peace to the whole world
为何霎哈嘉瑜伽的夫妇 不能和平共处 而我却对全世界说和平
It won't work out if you are fighting like that
若你们像这样争吵 那是不能成事的
Husband has to have complete understanding of his wife first
首先 丈夫要完全理解体谅妻子
And know that all the other women are like your sisters and mothers
亦要知道全世界的其他女人 等同是你的姊妹和母亲
If someone is not clean even after Sahaja Yoga then there's no way out
即使来霎哈嘉瑜伽后 若人的状况不清洁 就是没有出路
There was a swiss man not a Sahaja Yogi
有个瑞士男人 他不是霎哈嘉瑜伽士
Not Indian He was a father of a Sahaja Yogini
不是印度人 他是一个霎哈嘉女瑜伽士的父亲
Girl's husband had wandering eyes but came to sahaja yoga
女孩的丈夫有摇摆不定的眼睛 即使他已来霎哈嘉瑜伽
They both came to Sahaja Yoga The girl is very good but he went on doing it
他们两人都来了霎哈嘉瑜伽 女孩很好 但他仍继续这样
The non-yogi father told her to leave him
那个不是瑜伽士的父亲 告诉她离开他
"Even after sahaja yoga if he can't be cleansed then leave him"
即使来霎哈嘉瑜伽后 若他仍不清洁 离开他吧
"He is not a Sahaja Yogi don't relate with him"
他不是霎哈嘉瑜伽士 不要与他有任何关连
Even Non-Sahaja Yogi can understand that the person can't be cleansed
即使不是霎哈嘉瑜伽士也能明白 这个人不能得到洁净
He doesn't have stable attention then it is bad
他没有稳定的注意力 这很坏
Our culture is that men and women must be brother and sister
我们的文化是男女的关系必须是 兄弟姊妹的关系
But I see a talkative woman just go to talk to men
但我看到一个健谈的女人 她只与男人交谈
I don't understand it They don't sit with other ladies but with men
我就是不明白 她们不与其他女士 一起坐 只与男人一起坐
Same with men just start chatting with women
男人也一样 只与女人聊天
Even with maid or anyone just start talking, no self-esteem
无论那个女人是女仆 还是任何女人 开始说话 完全没有自尊
We think it's masculinity but Shri Rama is the perfect man who is highest
我们以为这是男子气概 罗摩是最高最完美的男人
But the one at the bottom think they are perfect
在底层的人却以为自己是完美的
Where is perfection? Not believing in Shri Rama but in devil
什么是完美 不相信罗摩 只相信邪魔
If you believe in Shri Rama follow his ideal
若你相信罗摩 就必须以祂为榜样
Therefore children and women are getting spoiled
因此 孩子被宠坏 女人也被宠坏
But still Indian women maintained good culture here
但这里的印度女人 仍能保持良好的印度文化
If they were like Americans what it would have been Men are fixed in terrible condition there
若她们像美国人 情况会是怎样 那里的男人境况很可怕
After 2-3 marriages Men becomes bunkrupt but women make a palace
在结两三次婚后 男人破产 女人却能建一所皇宫
It's bad in America Children are running away from home
在美国 情况很差 孩子离家出走
Indian woman manage their house husband and children
印度的妇女好好管理她们的房子 管理丈夫和孩子
But it's changing They think the same like husbands
但这些事情在转变 她们的想法与丈夫一样
If he runs away with 10 women then we go with 15 men
若他与十个女人私奔 我就和十五个男人私奔
If he is going to hell then I go before him
若他要进地狱 我比他先进地狱
Women shouldn't do it The base of dharma is in woman's hand
女人不应这样做 正法的根基在女人手上
Woman must manage husband dharmic making him understand
女人必须好好管理丈夫的正法 亦要令他明白
This is the biggest duty and power of woman to be Dharmaic
这是女人最大的责任和力量 就是要合乎正道
Biggest dharma is forgiveness Without it nothing works out
正法中最重要的正法是宽恕 没有宽恕 什么也成就不了
First thing she must have forgiveness Forgive children, husband
首先 她要有宽恕 宽恕孩子 宽恕丈夫
give refuge to house servants all are her duty
给予仆人庇护 这些全是女人的责任
This is the work that Shri Rama couldn't do neither Shri Krishna nor Shri Jesus
这些工作罗摩做不了 克里希纳和耶稣基督也做不了
Rama would have killed everyone who is useless, adharmic and flirt
罗摩会杀死没用的 反正法的 污秽不堪的人
Don't know how many he would be finished
我们不知道 祂还要令多少人完蛋
Krishna would use his sudarshan chakra and there would be a battle
克里希纳会运用 祂的sudarshan轮穴 那会有一场战争
Christ would crucify himself
基督会钉自己上十字架
One crucifiction is better than everyday
只钉上十字架一次 比每天都要钉上十字架好
Only Mother can do this work With such a power of love
只有母亲能这样做 以爱的力量
Anything can be worked out with her power of love
一切都能以她爱的力量来成就
She holds everything with so much love that children don't mind correcting
她以爱包容一切 因此 她的孩子不介意改正
For instance when trouble comes only mother knows how to handle it and scold later
例如 若有什么麻烦事发生 只有母亲知道怎样处理 她迟一点才去责骂
Because children understands mother's love and it is for them
因为孩子知道母亲爱他们 她做什么都是为他们好
With father children may react but not with mother's love without expectation
孩子或许会对父亲有反应 但不会对母亲 母亲的爱不期望任何回报
She doesn't want anything but her children to be good and get all my powers, all good in me
她什么也不要 只要她的孩子妥当 取得她所有的力量 她的所有优点
If mother feels it children will be fine
若母亲有这种想法 孩子就会妥当
But some mothers are very interfering and get involved in everything
但有些母亲很烦扰 她们干涉一切 染指一切
She comes always in front while husband is at the back
她常常站在前面 丈夫只能在后面
Children will be spoiled by it
若这样 孩子会被宠坏
Under such harmful environment children can be very emotional
在这种富伤害性的环境下 孩子可以很情绪化
So woman should be behind and make her husband in front
所以女人要站在后面 让她们的丈夫站在前面
Whatever husbands do wifes must help him behind
不管丈夫做什么 妻子都要在后面帮助他
The source of his power is wife Then how pure and hard-working she should be
他的力量源自妻子 妻子应是纯洁和勤勉的
I put everything on woman because I know you have great powers inside
我把一切都交给女人 因为我知道你们内在很有力量
Look at me as a Mother I must make everyone saints
看看我作为母亲 我要令每个人都成为圣人
Curing many diseases to make people saints
要治好很多疾病 令人成为圣人
Did anyone do this job? Only Ahilya was saved
还有谁在做着这些工作 只有Ahilya获得拯救
Jesus saved 21 people
耶稣拯救了二十一人
I must have saved 21000 now
到目前为此 我应拯救了二万一千人
Going around the world to do everyone's job
周游列国 做每个人的工作
it's still going on but I don't feel because of love
这种情况仍然持续 因为爱的力量 我不感到怎样
Maybe I should put bandhan as I don't know what kind of people I meet
或许出门前要做班丹 因为我不知道我会遇到什么人
But as soon as people comes to me I absorb all the problems
但一旦任何人来找我 我立即吸收了他们所有的问题
So love acts by itself I know everything is done by love
所以爱自动起作用 我知道是爱成就一切
I don't feel bad whatever happens Only Mother can bear the pain
不管什么发生 我没有坏感觉 只有母亲能承受这份痛苦
So I want you to grow consistantly without hurdles
我想你们能没有障碍的稳步成长
Also men should help their wives fully Understand and respect them
男人要全力帮助他们的妻子 体谅她们 尊重她们
Until the 2 wheels gets balanced the chariot doesn't go forward
除非战车的两个车轮能够平衡 不然它不会往前走
They both should be the same but one on the left and the other on the right
他们两人要一样 一个在左 一个在右
It won't work if you change it
若你改变他们的位置 就不合适了
It is moving and working because they are the same but unique
这两种车轮在运作 在工作 因为它们是相同又是不同
Same in the sense of height length and width but they work differently
相同在于高度 长度 阔度 但它们负责的工作却不同
It's the same in our life
同样情况发生在我们的生命里
Shri Rama didn't think only about husband and wife
所以罗摩不单只想着丈夫和妻子
Didn't think only about children and family
亦不单想着孩子和家庭
Also of brother, sister, mother, father and everyone as a normal human being
祂还想着兄弟 姊妹 母亲 父亲 每一个人 就如正常的人类一样
After he thought about society
之后 他才想及社会
About public, state and country
想及大众 也想及国家
As a human being he has shown human ideals in his activities
作为人类 祂透过活动 显示人类的典范该是怎么样
The person who loved his wife so much knew she was pure and hed left her
很爱妻子的人知道妻子是纯洁的 他离开她
Now people give so much to their own wife but they never give to poor people
现在 他们给妻子很多东西 却从不施予穷人什么
Otherwise they give to their relatives It's a disease among politicians
不然 亦把钱给亲人 这是政客的一种病
But the one who has wife who is sakshat devi had to leave her
妻子是sakshat devi的人 就要离开她
We must understand it's attachment to relatives and possessions
我们要明白 这是种执着依恋 依恋我们的亲人和财产
In west marriage relation wasn't alright but after Sahaja Yoga wife became everything
西方国家的婚姻关系不怎样妥当 在来霎哈嘉瑜伽后 妻子变成一切
Here leaders had to leave because their wives were not alright
这里的领袖要离开 因为他们的妻子不妥当
Their attention got spoiled by wife's preaching
透过妻子的鼓吹 他们的注意力受到破坏
At least five yogi left because of their wives
至少五个瑜伽士 因为他们的妻子而离开
Wives should understand Sahaja Yoga and their role in it
妻子必须明白霎哈嘉瑜伽和 他们在霎哈嘉瑜伽的角色
In this case husbands shouldn't agree with their wives at all
这种情况下 丈夫完全不应同意他们的妻子
Tell her that “You talk and move too much, Be quiet"
要告诉她 你说太多话 走得太多 请安静
You are useless Your chakras are not alright
你一无事处 你的轮穴亦不妥当
She will be alright only in this way
只有这样 她才会妥当
But instead you blame yourself and obey your wife?
但取而代之 你却责怪自己 仍遵从你的妻子
If she tells you to steal, you do it?
若她要你去偷窃 你会去吗
Even after Sahaja Yoga you still have some catches to take care
即使来霎哈嘉瑜伽后 你仍有些阻塞要处理
On the occasion of Shri Rama Hanuman should be remembered as his great devotee
今天在罗摩的庆典 我们要记着 哈奴曼作为罗摩伟大的虔敬者
And how he was busy at his service
哈奴曼是如何忙于事奉
He was aware that his life is for serving Shri Rama
祂知道自己的生命是为伺候罗摩
We should have his awereness in Sahaj Yoga
我们亦要对霎哈嘉瑜伽 采取同样的态度
But it doesn't mean you cook food for me which I don't eat
这不是说 你要为我煮我不吃的食物
You trouble me cooking so much this and that
你煮太多食物令我感到烦扰
Don't keep on serving someone forcefully
不要强迫人接受你的伺候
What we need is zeal to serve (Sewa)
我们要热心的去伺奉
Hanuman didn't serve food to Shri Rama
哈奴曼没有向罗摩端上食物
Delhi people kept on serving food so much
德里人透过烹调很多食物 令我感到烦扰
that I had to tell them I wouln't come if you don't stop
我因此要告诉他们 若你不停止 向我端上煮食物 我就不来
Do what you have to do
做你要做的事情
It's bad to force someone to eat
强迫人吃是很差劲的
serving one after another
有些人不停的端上食物
I don't need anything and I am tired
我什么也不需要 我对这种情况已感到很厌倦
I told you only flowers But don't spend too much also
我告诉你 只带些花朵来就行 但不要花太多钱来买花
A lot of flowers make me worry sometimes
有时太多花亦令我担忧
Please your Mother in balance She is a simple woman who don't understand these
以平衡的方式取悦你的母亲 她是个简单的女人 她不会明白这些
We have to learn that zeal to serve is from Hanuman ji
我们必须向哈奴曼 学习那份热情去侍奉
There is no special service for me
不用对我有特别的服务
But if you want to serve me serve to Sahaj Yoga
若你想服务我 就服务霎哈嘉瑜伽吧
Serving to Sahaja Yoga is serving to me
服务霎哈嘉瑜伽就是服务我
How many realisation have you given
你给了多少人自觉
How many did you transform and inspire
转化和启发了多少人
But if you say to new people they have bhoot, they just leave
若你对新来的人说 你有亡灵附着 他们会离开
One gentleman was told he has 3 bhoots in him so he left Sahaja Yoga
有人告诉这个男士 他有三个亡灵附着他 因此他离开了
he was told number of bhoots even
甚至有多少个亡灵也告诉他
he believed it because the Yogi was an authority in the local area
他相信因为告诉他的瑜伽士 是这地方有权势的大人物
I don't know who but the person left
我不知道这个大人物是谁 但这个人已经走了
So what we have to learn from Hanuman is the zeal
我们要向哈奴曼 学习什么是热切渴望
" Ram kaj karne ko tatpar" (eager to do Ram's work)
(渴望为罗摩办事)
What is our work? My work is sahaj yoga
什么是我们的工作 我的工作是霎哈嘉瑜伽
To raise kundalini
提升灵量
To make people peaceful and lovable talking about love
令人平和 有爱心 谈爱
Talk about Sahaja Yoga, about chakras Make them understand
对他们谈霎哈嘉瑜伽 谈轮穴 令他们明白
Doesn't mean you start giving lecture Some people started to give so much lecture
这不是说你要开始演讲 有些人演讲太多
I had to tell them to stop Otherwise Sahaja Yoga will be finished
我要告诉他们停止演讲 不然霎哈嘉瑜伽会完蛋
Only long lectures No time for Mother's talk and Aarti
说一个很长的讲话 却没时间听母亲的讲话和做摇灯礼
He said he just can't stop
他说他就是停不了
He doesn't know why "How can I fix it?"
他不知道为何会这样 我怎样可以改正
"You put supari (spice) in your mouth"
你放一点香料在口里
Then "How much?"
放多少
"It depends on the size of your mouth"
要看你的嘴巴有多大
"You don't know it even then how come you talk aobut Sahaja Yoga"
连放多少香料进嘴巴你也不知道 你怎能谈霎哈嘉瑜伽
you don't know it even
即使这样你也不知道
People like giving lecture
人们喜欢演讲
Get on a stage and won't leave a mic
走到台上 不愿意离开扩音器
Once with mic they cant't leave It's a new disease
一旦拿到扩音器 他们就是不走 这是一种新疾病
So you must understand why to give lecture
所以你们要明白 为什么要演讲
There are so many Mother's talk you can put a tape or video in every program
母亲已经有很多讲话 在每个讲座里 你们可以 播放母亲的录像带或录音带
After people can write question on paper And ask them to bring it next program
之后他们可以写下任何的问题 叫他们下次把问题带来
If there are someone who is sick or in trouble
若某人病了或有麻烦
Now there is a Yogi He comes to cure in Calcutta
有个瑜伽士 他来加尔各答为人治病
Now he was called to Russia
他现在被召去俄罗斯
One person is running like Hanuman all over to cure
他像哈奴曼那样四处去医治人
You all can cure All women can do
你们也能医治人 女人也可以
All men also But nobody tries
男人也可以 但却没有人尝试这样做
By giving lecture how many were cured?
透过演讲 有多少人得到医治
don't know what's the matter that till now there is only one man in India who can cure people
不知道出什么问题 直至现在 在印度 只有一个人能医治人
In London there are 15~20 people who can cure and in France also
在伦敦 有约十五至二十人 能医治人 法国也是
One should learn working on people like giving bandhan
你们要学习用什么方法医治人 像做班丹
No need to invite someone from abroad Remove Sahaja Yoga badges if you cannot cure
不需要邀请国外的人 若你不能医治人 把霎哈嘉瑜伽的标签除去吧
How do you work on others if you can't cure even yourself
若你连自己也治不好 又怎能治好别人
Everybody has got all the power to cure anyone
每个人都有能力医治人
Learn to become masters
学习成为导师
Instead of inviting someone They should go out to cure
而不是请别人来做 他们要走出去医治人
Just have some courage to work Nothing will happen
只要有勇气做这份工作 没什么会发生在你身上
By working, you become deeper like a tree grows deeper as it expands
透过这份工作 你变得更深入 就像树木扩展 它生长得更深
Sahaja Yogis are very much different from Incarnations
霎哈嘉瑜伽士 和降世神祇有很大分别
They have never worked in society before
他们从未在社会工作过
Nobody had the power for a mass
没有人曾经拥有这么多力量
Only one to one Like King Janaka to Nachiketa
只是一个给一个 就如Janak王给Nachiketa
But now you all have it Just grow it, that's all
但现在你们全都有力量 你只要成长 就这样
Cure yourself and others Understand Sahaja Yoga, you have everything
医治自己 医治别人 你明白霎哈嘉瑜伽 你拥有一切
But still your attention is wondering What are you running after?
但你的注意力仍散乱在四处 不知道自己在追寻什么
You still don't understand it Sahaja Yoga is just blessing
仍不明白 霎哈嘉瑜伽只是福佑
You won't be in short of anything
你不会缺乏什么
Just work for sahaja Yoga Even if you don't work you will be blessed
只要为霎哈嘉瑜伽做事 即使什么也不做 你也会受祝福
Business or promotion, this and that
生意扩展了 得到晋升
Everyone is blessed and nothing to give up
每个人都受到祝福 不需要放弃什么
Otherwise in time of freedom fight
我们为自由抗争的时候
we were tortured Lied on ice, got electric shocks
曾经被折磨 躺在冰块上 被电击
My parents went to jail Our house was sold
我父母进过多次监狱 我们的房子被出售
Lived in a hut... had to sacrifice a lot And you don't have to do it
我们要住在小屋里 要牺牲很多 你们却不用任何牺性
But not only recieving You have to give
你只是接受 但你也要付出
If one door is open so should be the other one Only one doesn't work
若一扇门打开 另一扇门也要打开 只开一扇门是不能成事
Everyone reports me about blessings they got
每个人都向我报告 他们有什么福佑
We must see what we have done for others
我们要看看自己为别人做了什么
But there are many fights for leadership It's all mother's play
很多人为想做领袖而争斗 这全是母亲的戏剧
You will know it when you will fall from there
当你从那里趺下 你就会知道
Specially women shouldn't get involved They fall very soon
特别是女人 不要牵涉入内 很快她们也会跌下
And men should know there is nothing like ministers
男人要知道没什么像总理
This is Mother's play Don't get involved in
这是母亲的戏剧 不要牵涉入内
Why I call a leader? It's a play There are no leaders
为何我称呼领袖只是一场戏 没有谁是领袖
It's just a test if you have ego If you have, you are gone
只是考验 若你有自我 若你有自我 你就会走
It will be shown immediately In Sahaja Yoga everything gets exposed
立即会显露出来 在霎哈嘉瑜伽 一切都会被揭露
Even if I say something it shows on the faces
即使我说了什么 也会在脸上表现出来
Once some leaders came and confessed their mistakes
有次有些领袖来 向我承认做错事
They have more responsibilities to be better, sweet, humble and loving
领袖肩负更多责任 要更好 更甜 更谦卑 更有爱心
and become close and sharing with everyone
与每个人融合 与每个人分享
Now on the auspicious occasion of Shri Rama we must understand what he had showen
在罗摩这个吉祥的日子 我们要明白祂的生命 向我们展示了什么
Only a bit of it would please our Mother
即使我们只能做到一点点 都能取悦母亲
He was in exile for a long time in Jungle Walked barefeet, worked so hard
祂长时间被放逐到森林里 赤脚行走 很辛勤的工作
Just to obey his father
只为遵从祂的父亲
Now to obey me you don't need to go into exile
现在 要遵从我 你不用离乡背井
Not barefeet, nor starving nothing All are there for you
不用赤脚走路 亦不用捱饿 一切都为你准备好
But you must know how to cure people in Sahaja Yoga
但在霎哈嘉瑜伽 你要知道怎样医治人
everything about sahaj yoga
要知道霎哈嘉瑜伽的一切
and mostly about love
而最重要要知道的是爱
it's nothing but power of love Everybody will be benefited
只是爱的力量 藉此每个人都得益
This is not only for special people
这不只是为特别的人而设
This is not only for one country but for the whole world
亦不只是为一个国家 而是为全世界而设
Watch how your attention is If it's disturbed we should correct it
看看你的注意力放在哪里 若注意力受骚扰 我们要纠正它
Put the power of spirit in it Do everything with concentration
把灵的力量放在注意力里 做任何事都要集中精神
And devotion and love will make you deep
虔敬和爱会令你有深度
Otherwise there is lots of rubbish
不然 会有很多垃圾
If you wish to stay like rubbish you know where it goes at the end
若你想象垃圾 你也知道垃圾最终会怎样
If you want to feel you are specially good capable of anything
若你以为自己很特别 能做任何事情
First humility, not only towards me but everyone
首先要谦卑 不是只对我 而是对每一个人
Talk humbly with love and show that people can blossom like lotus in Sahaja Yoga
以爱谦卑的说话 向人显示 在霎哈嘉瑜伽 人可以像莲花般盛放
to spread fragrance everywhere
他们的芬芳传播四周
People will tell me you are wonderful if you will do it in that way
若你这样做 人们会告诉我 你很令人赞叹
One day you too will be called as Maryada Purushottama
有天你们也会被称为 maryada purushottam
You are the temple of Rama so have it within yourself
你是罗摩的庙宇 因此你要有它在内
Perform puja to it Take care of your self-esteem
向它做崇拜 好好照顾你的自尊
Take the benefit of self-realization inside yourself
在你内在取得自觉的好处
You must have respect and devotion to it
你必须对它尊重和虔敬
"Now we are realized" "How can we do wrong, we are yogi"
我们现在已有自觉 我们怎能做错事 我们是瑜伽士
Soon you will have blessings immediately
很快你会拥有很多福佑 立即
As I am called Rokra devi, you will get blessing as soon as you assert it
就如我被称为 Rokra devi 一旦你维护它 你会得到福佑
Everyone is getting blessed with it give it back to the world
每个人都受它的祝福 再回报给全世界
Shri Rama used all his powers for the benevolence of people to show the ideal
就如罗摩把祂所有力量用在 人民的福祉上 展示祂为榜样典范
You will be surprised to achieve so high when the time comes
你会很惊讶 当时候到了 你们都有很高的成就
You won't have any disease and all bad habits will be dropped
你不会有任何疾病 所有坏习惯亦会戒掉
You will eat, talk and watch as much as you need
你需要时才吃 需要时才说话 需要时才看
You will watch your mind for introspection
你会因内省而观察自己的思维
"Where is my mind going?" "I'm a Sahaja Yogi, stop it"
我在想什么 我是霎哈嘉瑜伽士 停止这样吧
By doing so you will be in meditation
透过这样做 你会在入静中
Your kundalini will be satisfied and give you blessings
你的灵量亦会很满足 并赐予你祝福
You say, "Mother what a blessing"
那么你就会说 母亲 这是何等的福佑
But you have to jump into it Only then will you know it
但你要跳进去 只有这样你才会知道
Till then you need to work hard
直到那时候 你还需要辛勤工作
Shri Rama was born at midnight so let's have puja late
罗摩是在午夜出生 所以让我们迟一点才开始崇拜
Shri Rama Puja is not a specially long one
罗摩的崇拜也不特别长
As he is in a human form he is humanity within us
因为祂是以人类的形相 祂是我们内在的人性
by which we understand our intellect and our thoughts get changed
藉此我们明白知性 我们的思维亦得到改变
Shri Rama is that Through him we can change our thoughts
罗摩就是这样 透过罗摩 我们改变我们的想法
Our nature can change Because he is our ideal
亦改变了我们的本质 因为祂是我们的榜样典范
After achieving his ideals we reach another because he was human ideal
当我们到达祂的典范 我们就能到其他典范 因为祂是人类的典范
It is great that God came to this world in a human form to became our ideal
神以人的形相来到这个世界 是很了不起的 祂成为我们的典范
He has gone through all the hardships to show us strength to keep Dharma
祂经历所有困难 向我们显示要有力量持守正法
That is Vishwa Dharma and the state of yoga
即普世无沾正法 和瑜伽的状态
May God bless you all
愿神祝福你们